Your source of Islamic literature presents, the Lives of Prophets Part One.
In Part One Imam Anwar Al-Awlaki will cover the lives of Adam عليه السّلام though Younas عليه السّلام.
أعوذ بالله من الشيطان الرجيم ۞
بِسمِ اللَّهِ الرَّحمٰنِ الرَّحيمِ۞
فَٱقْصُصِ ٱلْقَصَصَ لَعَلَّهُمْ يَتَفَكَّرُونَ۞
So relate the stories, perhaps they may reflect.
Adam(آدَم),
Sheeth(شيث‎),
Idrees(إدريس),
Noah(نوح),
Hud(هود),
Salih(صالح),
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم),
Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل),
Is'haq(إسحَاقّ),
Lut(لوط),
Yaqoob(يعقوب),
Yusuf(يوسف),
Shoaib(شعيب),
Ayyub(ايوب),
Zul Kifl(ذوالكفل),
Musa(موسى),
Haroon(هارون),
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون),
Al-Yasa(أليسع),
Ilyas(إلياس),
Daud(داؤد),
Sulaiman(سليمان),
Yunus(يونس),
Zakariya(زكريَّة),
Yahya(يحي),
Eesa(عيسى),
Muhammad صلى الله عليه وسلم وصلوات الله والسلام عليه اجمعين.
أو۟لَـٰٓئِكَ ٱلَّذِينَ هَدَى ٱللَّهُ ۖ فَبِهُدَىٰهُمُ ٱقْتَدِهْ
They are those, whom Allah has guided, so follow their guidance.
THE LIVES OF THE PROPHETS
أعوذ بالله من الشيطان الرجيم ۞
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمٰنِ الرَّحِيْمِ۞
إن الحمد لله، نحمده ونستعينه ونستغفره ونستهديه،
ونعوذ بالله من شرور أنفسنا ومن سيئات أعمالنا،
من يهده الله فلا مضل له ومن يضلل فلا هادي له،
وأشهد أن لا إله إلا الله وحده لا شريك له وأشهد أن محمداً عبده ورسوله،
وأدى الأمانة , ونصح الأمة , وجاهد في الله حق جهاده،
امَّا بعد
فانَّ اَصدق الحديث كتاب الله وخير الهدي،
هدي محمدٍ صلى الله عليه وسلم
وشرَّ الأمورِ محدثاتُها وكلَّ محدثتٍ بدعةٍ ،
وكل بدعة ضلالةٌ ، وكلَّ ضلالةٍ في النارِ
نَحْنُ نَقُصُّ عَلَيْكَ أَحْسَنَ ٱلْقَصَصِ بِمَآ أَوْحَيْنَآ إِلَيْكَ هَـٰذَا ٱلْقُرْءَانَ وَإِن كُنتَ مِن قَبْلِهِۦ لَمِنَ ٱلْغَـٰفِلِينَ۞
Allah سبحانه وتعالى ‎says;
We relate unto you, O Muhammad(محمد), the best of stories through Our revelations unto you of this Qur'an,
and before this, you were among those who weren’t aware of it.
It is from Allah.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى is the One, Who is revealing this to Muhammad ﷺ and to this Ummah(أمة‎).
نَحْنُ نَقُصُّ عَلَيْكَ أَحْسَنَ ٱلْقَصَصِ
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says: We relate unto you the best of stories.
These are the best of stories because they are dealing with the best of creation.
Some of the benefits of talking about the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء);
Number 1;
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ was commanded to do so.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
فَٱقْصُصِ ٱلْقَصَصَ
Relate unto them the stories.
It's a command from Allah سبحانه وتعالى given to Rasool Allah ﷺ
Allah سبحانه وتعالى is commanding him that, you must narrate these stories unto the Ummah(امة).
So, it becomes a duty upon us to relate these stories.
It becomes mandatory on us to convey the message of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى and their stories.
So number 1, we are doing this as a Ibadah(عبادة) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى, to fulfill a commandment of Allah.
Number 2;
لَعَلَّهُمْ يَتَفَكَّرُونَ۝
فَٱقْصُصِ ٱلْقَصَصَ لَعَلَّهُمْ يَتَفَكَّرُونَ۝
Relate and convey to them the stories.
Why?
So that they may reflect.
لَعَلَّهُمْ يَتَفَكَّرُونَ۝
So they may contemplate.
Al-Tafakkur(التفكر)
these stories are not to entertain us.
These stories are for us to derive lessons, and reflect,
and to contemplate, and to think about, to deeply reflect on them,
that is what we need to do.
Number 3;
Another reason why it's extremely important to study the stories of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says:
أُوْلَـٰئِكَ ٱلَّذِينَ هَدَى ٱللَّهُ فَبِهُدَاهُمُ ٱقْتَدِهْ
They are those, whom Allah has guided, so follow their guidance.
They are the ones who are guided,
and Allah سبحانه وتعالى is instructing Rasool Allah ﷺ to follow them, to follow their guidance,
because they are the best.
We need to have role models.
It is very important for the human being to have models, especially in the early stages of our life.
You find that every human being has role models
if they are not good, they're gonna be bad.
That is our make-up as human beings;
we must have some role models, we must have some people whom we look up to.
If we’re not going to provide our children and our youth with the role models of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء)
and the role models of Rasool Allah ﷺ and the role models of the Sahabah(صحابه),
they’re gonna find role models somewhere else, because human beings cannot live without role models.
And Allah سبحانه وتعالى is telling Muhammad ﷺ that he must follow the way of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
If this instruction was given to Rasool Allah ﷺ, then what should we do?
فَبِهُدَىٰهُمُ ٱقْتَدِهْ
Allah سبحانه وتعالى is commanding Rasool Allah ﷺ to follow their way.
So we need to study the lives of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى
so that they can become our role models.
Number 4;
TO LOVE THEM.
Al-Mahabbah(المحبة).
If you do not know someone, you cannot love him.
We all claim that we love the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah.
But if we don't know the details of their life,
we don't know what they went through,
how could we have respect for them?
Abu Dharr(أبوذر) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and asked him a question.
قال كم عدة الأنبياء؟
What is the total number of Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء)?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مائة وعشرون ألفا الرسل من ذلك ثلاثمائة وخمسة عشر جما غفيرا
What is the number of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء)?
120,000 and the messengers among them are 315.
So the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى are 120,000
and the messengers, Al-Rusul(الرسل), are 315.
I’m translating Nabi(نبي) as “Prophet” and Rasool(رسول) as “Messenger”.
So there are two different things, Nabi(نبي) and Rasool(رسول);
Nabi (نبي), the plural of it is Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء),
Rasool(رسول), the plural of it is Rusul(رسل).
So what is the difference between the Nabi(نبي) and the Rasool(رسول)?
What is the difference between the Prophet and the Messenger?
There are a few opinions of the Ulema(علماء‎) in this;
one of them is that the Rasool(رسول) is the Nabi(نبي) who is given a law.
The Rasool(رسول) is a Nabi(نبي) who is given a law,
but the Nabi(نبي) who is not a Rasool(رسول) is following the law of another Rasool(رسول).
So every Rasool(رسول) is a Nabi(نبي), but not every Nabi(نبي) is a Rasool(رسول).
Every Prophet is not a Messenger, but every Messenger is a Prophet.
If a Prophet is given a new law, then he becomes a Rasool(رسول) and a Nabi(نبي).
If he’s not given a new law, then he is a Nabi(نبي) - only a Prophet.
An example of that to make it little bit clearer Musa(موسی) is a Rasool(رسول).
Musa(موسی) is a Rasool(رسول).
Why?
Because he was given the Tawrah(توراة‎).
But Harun(هارون) is not a Rasool(رسول),
Harun(هارون) is a Nabi(نبي).
Why?
Because he is following the law of his brother.
Harun(هارون) is following the law of Musa(موسی).
This is one difference that the Ulema(علماء‎) gave to between Nabi(نبي) and Rasool(رسول).
But before we start talking about Adam(آدم‎), let's look at the story of creation.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was asked this question by a group who came from Yemen,
and this is narrated in Bukhari(بخاری‎).
They came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they said;
يا رسول الله ما أول هذا الأمر؟
"O Rasool Ullah, how did all of this start?"
They wanna know how this all came into existence.
فقال صلى الله عليه وسلم
كَانَ اللَّهُ ولم يكن معه شيء، وفي رواية: ولم يكن قبله شيء،
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: "In the beginning, there was Allah,
There was nothing before Him," another narration. "Nothing was with Him."
وكان عرشه على الماء
"And His throne was on water."
وكتب في الذكر كل شىء،
"And He wrote in the tablet everything."
وخلق السموات والأرض
"And He created the heavens and the earth."
Again;
عن عمران بن حصين قال أهل اليمن لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
جئناك لنتفقه في الدين ولنسألك عن أول هذا الأمر
فقال كان اللَّه ولم يكن شىء قبله،
وكان عرشه على الماء، وكتب في الذكر كل شىء، وخلق السموات والأرض
Narrated by Al-Bukhari(البخاري‎), Imran bin Husain(عمران بن حصين) said;
People from Yemen came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
We have came to you to learn our religion and to ask you, "How did all of this start?"
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
There was Allah and nothing before Him, and His throne was on water,
and He wrote everything in the tablet, and He created the heavens and earth.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
إن أول ما خلق الله القلم،
ثم قال له: اكتب، فجرى في تلك الساعة بما هو كائن إلى يوم الساعة
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: The first thing Allah created was the Pen,
then Allah ordered it to write so it wrote everything that will happen until the Day of Judgment.
We worry about rizq(رزق),
we worry about our rizq(رزق).
Rizq(رزق) is sustenance, what Allah will provide us.
We worry about our wealth,
we’re always thinking about tomorrow, we are Rizq-o-Phobic.
We have a problem of paranoia of Rizq(رزق).
خلق الإنسان هلوعا
We’re always in a state of despair when it comes to wealth.
We’re always thinking about, “How will we make it in the future?”
worried and terrified and paranoid.
Well listen to this.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in a Hadith(حديث) narrated by Muslim(ألمسلم).
كتب اللَّه مقادير الخلائق قبل أن يخلق السموات والأرض بخمسين ألف سنة
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in the Hadith(حديث) narrated by Muslim(ألمسلم);
Allah wrote down the sustenance of the creation 50,000 years before He created the heavens and the earth.
Everything that you will get is already written down, not 50,000 years before this day,
but 50,000 years before the heavens and the earth were created.
It's a done deal, what you will get is already written down.
Are you still going to be very concerned about it?
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
خلقت الملائكة من نور وخلق الجان من مارج من نار
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: The angels were created from light and the Jin(جن) were created from fire.
So these are two other creations beside the human being which we know about.
The angels, whom were created from light, and the Jin(جن‎), they were created from fire.
Iblees(إبليس) was from Al-Jinn(الجن),
but because he was so righteous,
he was included with the angels and elevated to a very high level among the angels,
even though he was from Al-Jinn(الجن).
Adam(آدم‎) was created from dirt.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَإِذْ قَالَ رَبُّكَ لِلْمَلَـٰئِكَةِ إِنِّى جَاعِلٌ فِى ٱلْأَرْضِ خَلِيفَةً
And remember when your Lord said to the angels;
“Verily, I am going to place mankind generations after generations on Earth.”
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
إِنِّى جَاعِلٌ فِى ٱلْأَرْضِ خَلِيفَةً
Allah is telling the angels; I will place on Earth a Khalifah(خليفه).
What does “Khalifah(خليفة)” mean?
“Khalifah(خليفة)” comes from the word “khalaf(خلف)”,
and khalaf(خلف) means to succeed someone else or to assume the position of someone else.
These are the meanings of the word khalaf(خلف).
Allah سبحانه وتعالى, for example, says in Qur’an;
فَخَلَفَ مِنۢ بَعْدِهِمْ خَلْفٌ أَضَاعُوا۟ ٱلصَّلَوٰةَ وَٱتَّبَعُوا۟ ٱلشَّهَوَٰتِ ۖ فَسَوْفَ يَلْقَوْنَ غَيًّا۞
A generation followed them, who lost prayer and followed desires, so they will be misguided.
In this Ayah(آية), it means a generation that came after them,
and that is why we have salaf(سلف‎) and khalaf(خلف).
We say salaf(سلف‎) - who are the salaf(سلف‎)?
The salaf(سلف‎) are the early 3 generations.
Everyone who comes after them, we call them khalaf(خلف).
And then what was Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) called when he assumed responsibility after Rasool Allah ﷺ?
خليفة رسول الله
The Khalifah(خليفه) of Rasool Ullah.
Why?
Because he assumed responsibility after Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he came after Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So we see that, in this word, which was used in reference of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), it has two meanings;
first meaning is that he's assuming the responsibility of leading the Ummah(امة) after Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and the second meaning it says that he is coming after Rasool Ullah - Khalifah(خليفة), he comes after.
If we would apply these two meanings to the responsibility or the title that was given to humanity,
Allah سبحانه وتعالى said;
إِنِّى جَاعِلٌ فِى ٱلْأَرْضِ خَلِيفَةً
I will place a Khalifah(خليفه) on Earth.
So we find two explanations were given;
One explanation says that Allah سبحانه وتعالى has appointed Adam(آدم‎)
and his children, his descendants, in the position of responsibility to apply the Laws of Allah سبحانه وتعالى,
so they are representing the Law of Allah سبحانه وتعالى on Earth.
They are given the responsibility of applying the Law of Allah سبحانه وتعالى on Earth
and that is the explanation given by Ibn Mas'ud(ابن مسعود).
The second explanation is that humans beings would succeed each other in this world, generation after generation,
and this is the opinion of Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس).
Our responsibility on Earth is to establish Earth according to the Laws of Allah سبحانه وتعالى,
and also we see that we are succeeding each other.
We’re not like the angels who are living, and they’re not marrying and having children.
And we succeed each other on this earth,
that’s why Allah سبحانه وتعالى says about the people of Aad(عاد),
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says that you became the Khalaef(خلائف) of the earth,
which is plural of “Khalifah(خليفة)”, after the people of Nuh(نوح).
So this is the meaning of the word “Khalifah(خليفة)”.
If we look at the Ayah(آية) before this, it would help us in understanding our mission and our role in this world.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says in the Ayah(آية) right before this Ayah(آية);
هُوَ الَّذي خَلَقَ لَكُم ما فِي الأَرضِ جَميعًا ثُمَّ استَوىٰ إِلَى السَّماءِ
ثُمَّ استَوىٰ إِلَى السَّماءِ فَسَوّاهُنَّ سَبعَ سَماواتٍ ۚ وَهُوَ بِكُلِّ شَيءٍ عَليمٌ۝
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has created for you everything in this world.
Everything in this world was created for the human being.
That is the honor that Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given this human being,
that everything is created for the exploitation of human beings
because they are the ultimate creation of this world
and they are the ones whom Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given the responsibility of establishing this Duniya(دنيا‎), this world.
So Allah سبحانه وتعالى has created everything for them.
Therefore, we should not give precedence to anything material over the human being.
We should not sacrifice the human being for a material thing
because Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given this noble position to human being
and he made them a Khalifah(خليفة) and he created everything for this human being;
the human being is sacred.
But the way we are dealing with the human being now on the face of the earth
is that we are killing human beings and destroying them for material gain,
and that's why Rasool Allah ﷺ says that the Muslim is sacred in the Eyes of Allah سبحانه وتعالى more than Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
حرمة دم المسلم
The sanctity and the sacred position that is given to the blood of the Muslim is more than Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
That is the honor that Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given to the son of Adam(آدم‎).
وَلَقَدْ كَرَّمْنَا بَنِى ءَادَمَ
We have honored the son of Adam(آدَم).
When Allah سبحانه وتعالى told the angels that I will place a Khalifah(خليفه) on Earth,
what did they say?
They said;
قالوا أَتَجعَلُ فيها مَن يُفسِدُ فيها وَيَسفِكُ الدِّماءَ
وَنَحنُ نُسَبِّحُ بِحَمدِكَ وَنُقَدِّسُ لَكَ
Will You place therein those who will make mischief therein and shed blood
while we glorify You with praises and thanks?
Are You going to place on Earth someone who will shed blood and cause corruption
when we are glorifying You?
How did the angels know that human beings will corrupt on the face of the earth?
Adam(آدم‎) was not placed on the world yet.
Why did the angels say, “You are going to place someone who will cause corruption and shed blood in the world”?
There are two explanations given;
One explanation is that Allah سبحانه وتعالى told the angels ahead of time that
this is what human beings will do;
the second explanation, and this is mentioned by Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس),
that Jin(جن) were living in this world before
and they caused corruption and they shed blood
and they fought with each other and they corrupted this world,
and they caused so much evil,
and then Allah سبحانه وتعالى sent on them armies from the angels, and also Iblees(إبليس), to fight against them,
and then they were pushed and cornered to the islands of the ocean.
So the angels said;
Why are You going to place someone on Earth who would cause corruption and shed blood again?
So these are the two explanations given,
there is no Hadith(حديث‎) to support any one of them.
These are two explanations given to the Ayah(آية).
Allah سبحانه وتعالى said;
قالَ إِنّي أَعلَمُ ما لا تَعلَمونَ۞
I know what you know not.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى created Adam(آدم‎) and Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
إن اللَّه تعالى خلق آدم من قبضة قبضها من جميع الأرض
فجاء بنو آدم على قدر الأرض
جاء منهم الأحمر والأبيض والأسود وبين ذلك
والسهل والحزن والخبيث والطيب وبين ذلك
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
Allah created Adam(آدَم) from a handful of dirt, picked from all of the Earth,
so the children of Adam(آدَم) became red, white and black, and everything in between,
and they became soft and tough, bad and good, and everything in between.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
Allah سبحانه وتعالى created Adam(آدم‎) from a handful of dirt.
This dirt was taken from different parts of the earth.
So there was black soil, there was white soil, there was yellow soil, different colors.
And then some of this soil was taken from mountains, and some of it was taken from valleys, and it was mixed together.
So the son of Adam(آدم‎), the descendants of Adam(آدم‎), came out in different colors
because the dirt they were created from is from different colors,
and they came out with different qualities
because some of this dirt was taken from mountains, and some of it was valleys,
some of it was from fertile land, and some of it was from infertile land.
So you have some of them are righteous and some of them are evil,
some of them are easy to deal with and some of them are tough.
They came out according to the material they were created from.
What was Adam(آدم‎) created from?
Turab(تراب‎),
dirt.
But that was not the only name that was given to the material we were created from.
We find in Qur’an that the components of our body were described with different terms.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has called it Turab(تراب‎),
which means dirt;
Allah has called it Tin(طين),
which means clay;
Tinin Laazib(طين لازب), sticky clay;
Salsal(صلصال),
sounding clay;
Hama’im Masnoon(حمإ مسنون),
black smooth mud.
Why were these different terms used to refer to the material we were created from?
Turab(تراب‎),
tin(طين),
Salsal(صلصال),
Hama’im masnoon(حمإ مسنون),
Tinin Laazib(طين لازب)
dirt,
mud,
clay,
sounding clay,
black smooth mud.
In the beginning, it was dirt.
turab(تراب‎)
dirt, soil that was taken from the earth,
and that is turab(تراب‎).
And then this dirt was mixed with the basis of every living being, and that is water.
وَجَعَلنا مِنَ الماءِ كُلَّ شَيءٍ حَيٍّ ۖ
We created from water every living being.
When it was mixed with water, it became mud, tin(طين).
And then this mud was left for a while,
and when you leave mud for a while and the moisture in it reduces, it becomes sticky.
In the beginning, it is loose mud because it has a lot of water,
then when the water level decreases and the moisture decreases,
it becomes sticky
and it holds to your hands; sticky,
and that is Tin Laazib(طين لازب), sticky clay.
And then that sticky clay was left for a longer while,
the smell of it changed and the color of it became darker,
and that is Hama’im Masnoon(حمإ مسنون),
which is black, smooth, and smelly clay
because it was left there for a while.
That material was taken, and Allah سبحانه وتعالى molded out of it the form of Adam(آدم‎), the body of Adam(آدم‎).
That body was left to dry, and it turned into Salsal Kal-Fakhar(صلصال كَٱلفخار)
clay-like pottery.
When you knock on dry clay, pottery, what happens?
It makes a ringing sound,
and that is Salsal(صلصال), Min Salsalah(من صلصلة), it makes a ringing sound like a bell.
So the body, the form of Adam(آدم‎), the empty form of Adam(آدم‎) that did not have the soul yet, it was just a material.
It was left to dry, and then when you would knock on it, it would make this ringing sound.
It is said, this is not a Hadith(حديث), but it is said that Iblis(إبليس), he saw this body lying on the ground.
He didn’t know what it was,
so Iblis(إبليس) walked up to the body of Adam(آدم‎) and he knocked it,
and it made a ringing sound and it was hollow.
When he knocked it, he knew that it was hollow from the inside, empty.
He said;
هذا خلق لا يتمالك
When he found out that it’s hollow, he said;
This is a creation that is weak.
It’s hollow from the inside.
And then he said;
لن يسلط عليك لهينك ولا أن يسلط علي لا عصيانك
If I am given influence over you, I will guide you astray
and if you are given influence over me, I would disobey you.
He is our enemy from day one.
Adam(آدَم) is not even alive yet,
it's just a body that is lying there, and he said;
If you are given influence over me, I'm going to disobey you.
Let's do the same thing and disobey him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in the Hadith(حديث) narrated by Muslim(ألمسلم);
خلق الله آدم على صورته
In the beginning, we know that Allah سبحانه وتعالى has created Adam(آدَم) with His own Hands.
Adam(آدَم) was honored that he was created with the Hands of Allah سبحانه وتعالى,
a great honor and that is mentioned in the Hadith(حديث) of Al-shafa'ah(الشفاعة‎)
when the humans would go to Sayyiduna Adam(سيدنا آدم‎) on the Day of Judgment, and they would say;
You are the one whom Allah سبحانه وتعالى blew his soul into you
and you are the one whom Allah سبحانه وتعالى created with His own Hands
and you are the one whom Allah سبحانه وتعالى made the angels bow down to, to make Sujud(سجود).
Honoring that Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given to Adam(آدم‎), he was created with the Hands of Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in the Hadith(حديث) narrated by Muslim(ألمسلم);
خلق الله آدم على صورته
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has created Adam(آدَم) on his image.
On his image.
Al-Nawawi(النووي‎) gives an explanation to this Hadith(حديث).
He says;
What is meant by, Allah has created Adam(آدَم) on his image?
It is not talking about the Image of Allah, it is talking about the image of Adam(آدَم).
Allah created Adam(آدَم) on the image of Adam(آدَم).
You might wonder, What does that mean?
What do you mean Allah created Adam(آدَم) on Adam's image?
That would mean that Allah سبحانه وتعالى created Adam(آدَم) as he was in his adult form that remained with him.
In other words, Adam(آدَم) did not go through the stages that we go through;
of being an embryo, and then a fetus, and then an infant, and then a child, and then an adult.
خلق الله آدم على صورته
Adam(آدم‎) was created on his image,
he didn't go through changes of images like we do.
We go through different changes of images;
from embryo to fetus…
it looks very different when you go from the one cell to another…
then it multiplies, and the embryo is in the early stages, and then the fetus.
If you look at it, the image could change within days.
But with Adam(آدم‎), he was created on that image from day One,
and this is diametrically opposed to what the Theory of Evolution says.
The Theory of Evolution states that human beings came through an evolution process
that started with a chemical reaction
and then the one cell, the single cell, and then multiple cells,
and then it goes up and up and up until it reaches to the human being in the end of that long chain.
That is contradicting, completely contradicting, to the truth
because Allah سبحانه وتعالى has created Adam(آدم‎) with His own Hands on that image
that remained with Adam(آدم‎) until he died.
But let me say that Islam does not completely disapprove everything in the Theory of Evolution;
Islam disapproves some and approves some.
Islam disapproves the part of the Theory of Evolution that states that nature is the creator or that things came out of random.
Islam is against the part of the Theory of Evolution that states that human being evolved from a single cell
and then it went up to the ape, which they call the closest relative of the human being, and then the human being.
But Islam is not opposed to the part of the Theory of Evolution that says that species adapt to their environment.
We see that around us, that different species learn how to adapt to different environments.
But, we say that that happens with the Will of Allah.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى blew the soul into Adam(آدم‎).
Ar-Ruh(الروح).
Our body without Ar-Ruh(الروح) is part of the earth, it is dirt.
Our body is made up of carbon, oxygen, copper, iron, sulfur that is our body.
And when the soul leaves, our body decomposes into its origin.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
مِنْهَا خَلَقْنَـٰكُمْ وَفِيهَا نُعِيدُكُمْ وَمِنْهَا نُخْرِجُكُمْ تَارَةً أُخْرَىٰ
We created you from Earth, and you will return to Earth, and then We will resurrect you again from Earth.
We are nothing without the soul.
The essence of life is not in this materialistic body,
this body that we have is dead, it is material components that are dirt, it came from the dirt, from the earth.
What puts life in us is the soul, and that is the secret of life
and it remains as a secret even with all of the advancement in science and technology that we have.
They came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said: Tell us about the soul.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَيَسْـَٔلُونَكَ عَنِ ٱلرُّوحِ ۖ قُلِ ٱلرُّوحُ مِنْ أَمْرِ رَبِّى وَمَآ أُوتِيتُم مِّنَ ٱلْعِلْمِ إِلَّا قَلِيلًا۝
They ask you about the soul. Tell them that the knowledge of the soul belongs to Allah,
and you have been given very limited knowledge.
The soul is a secret that only Allah knows,
and our knowledge of the soul is very limited.
This question was asked to Rasool Allah ﷺ fourteen hundred years ago;
our knowledge about the soul did not change much since then.
We don’t know much about the soul.
The Soviet Union, under communism, they disbelieved in anything metaphysical.
They only believed in the physical world; everything that is metaphysical, they didn't believe in it.
So they thought that they could create a human being,
so in their labs, they looked at the composition of the human body
and they found out that it’s made of copper, and sulfur, and iron, and carbon, and oxygen, and hydrogen.
They brought those elements and they mixed them together with the same ratio that exists in our body,
and then they kept on sending some electrical shocks on it thinking that that would give it life.
It is not our body that makes us alive, our body is dirt, it belongs to this earth.
What makes us alive is the secret which Allah سبحانه وتعالى has placed in us, and that is the soul, Ar-Ruh(الروح).
And that is something we don’t know about.
That is the difference between life and death, Ar-Ruh(الروح).
That is why when Musa(موسی) and the magicians were competing,
the magicians were throwing their sticks
and they were making those sticks look like snakes through optical illusion,
but with Musa(موسی), his stick turned into an actual living snake
because Allah سبحانه وتعالى’s the One, Who controls life,
so Allah put life in that stick and it became a snake.
But with the magicians, all what they could do is fool the people through an optical illusion
because they do not have the power to put life,
and when they saw what was happening with the stick of Musa(موسی), they knew that this is a miracle
and they immediately became Muslim
because they knew that this is something outside the capacity and the capability of the human being.
So the soul is what gives us life, and this is as Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
مِنْ أَمْرِ رَبِّى
This is knowledge that belongs to Allah, this is an issue that belongs to Allah.
When the soul entered into the body of Adam(آدم‎), the first thing that happened is,
he sneezed.
When the soul entered into his body, Adam(آدم‎) sneezed.
لما خلق اللَّه آدم ونفخ فيه الروح عطس
Rasool Allah ﷺ says when Allah سبحانه وتعالى created Adam(آدم‎) and He blew the soul into him,
Adam(آدم‎) sneezed.
فقال الحمد للَّه
Adam(آدم‎) said: Al-hamdulillah(ألحمدلله).
“Praise be to Allah.”
Allah سبحانه وتعالى told him;
يرحمك اللَّه
“The Mercy of Allah be upon you.”
The first thing that happened to Adam(آدم‎) was the deliverance of mercy onto him from Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
When he was created, Allah سبحانه وتعالى Himself told Adam(آدم‎);
يرحمك اللَّه
The Mercy of Allah be upon you.
That was the first thing that was told to Sayyiduna Adam عليه السلام.
He had the Mercy of Allah سبحانه وتعالى from the beginning.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى told him;
اذهب إلى أولئك الملائكة إلى نفر منهم جلوس
Allah سبحانه وتعالى told Adam(آدم‎): “Go to those angels who are sitting over there.”
Allah سبحانه وتعالى told Adam(آدم‎) to go to those angels and to deliver Salam(سلام‎) to them.
اذهب إلى أولئك الملائكة إلى نفر منهم جلوس فقل السلام عليكم
“Go to those angels who are sitting over there and tell them;
السلام عليكم
Allah سبحانه وتعالى is teaching Adam(آدم‎),
“Go to those angels and tell them;
السلام عليكم
Adam(آدم‎) went up to the angels and he said;
السلام عليكم‏!‏
قالوا وعليك السلام ورحمة اللَّه
He went to the angels, he told them;
السلام عليكم
They said;
وعليك السلام ورحمة اللَّه وبركاته
“May the Peace of Allah سبحانه وتعالى be upon you and His Mercy be upon you and His Blessings be upon you.”
So Adam(آدم‎) came back to Allah سبحانه وتعالى, Allah told him;
إن هذه تحيتك وتحية بنيك بينهم
“This is your greeting and this is the greeting of your descendents.”
So Allah سبحانه وتعالى has taught us our greeting from the beginning
and it was taught to Adam عليه السلام, and this is the greeting that Allah سبحانه وتعالى wanted for the children of Adam(آدم‎).
It is; Assalam O Alaikum(السلام عليكم).
“Peace be upon you.
” Not “hi”, “hello”, “good morning”, or “good night”, or “what's up”.
السلام عليكم
Peace be upon you, first,
and then after that, after you deliver the peace…
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) look at the beauty of Islam, we are spreading peace.
أفشوا السلام بينكم
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: “Spread peace among you.”
Spread peace whenever you see somebody,
السلام عليكم
“Peace be upon you.”
Alhamdulillah (الحمد لله) on the Niʿmah(نعمة) of being Muslim.
After you say;
السلام عليكم
And you receive the blessing of your brother telling you;
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته
Then you are free to use any greeting you want,
whether it is “hi” or “hello” or “good morning” or “good afternoon” or “storestee” or “صح خبس”, or “cómo estás”...or whatever, whatever you want…
”Sabah al-khayr(صباح الخير)”.
In the beginning, Assalam O Alaikum(السلام عليكم).
And then after that you could use any greeting you want
because we know that Rasool Allah ﷺ used to tell the Sahabah(صحابة) for example: Kaifa Asbahat(كيف أصبحت)”.
“Kaifa Asbaht(كيف أصبحت)” is like saying “good morning”.
But in the beginning, it needs to be:
السلام عليكم
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَإِذْ أَخَذَ رَبُّكَ مِنۢ بَنِىٓ ءَادَمَ مِن ظُهُورِهِمْ ذُرِّيَّتَهُمْ
وَأَشْهَدَهُمْ عَلَىٰٓ أَنفُسِهِمْ أَلَسْتُ بِرَبِّكُمْ ۖ
قَالُوا۟ بَلَىٰ ۛ شَهِدْنَآ ۛ أَن تَقُولُوا۟ يَوْمَ ٱلْقِيَـٰمَةِ
أَن تَقُولُوا۟ يَوْمَ ٱلْقِيَـٰمَةِ إِنَّا كُنَّا عَنْ هَـٰذَا غَـٰفِلِينَ ۝
أَوْ تَقُولُوٓا۟ إِنَّمَآ أَشْرَكَ ءَابَآؤُنَا مِن قَبْلُ وَكُنَّا ذُرِّيَّةً مِّنۢ بَعْدِهِمْ ۖ
أَفَتُهْلِكُنَا بِمَا فَعَلَ ٱلْمُبْطِلُونَ۝
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
And remember when your Lord brought forth from the children of Adam(آدَم) from their loins their seed
and made them testify as to themselves, saying: “Am I not your Lord?”
They said: “Yes, we testify.”
Lest you should say on the Day of Resurrection: “Verily, we have been unaware of this.”
This is talking about a very important concept, and that is Al-Mithaq(الميثاق), the covenant.
Do you know that there is an agreement between us and Allah سبحانه وتعالى?
Do you know that there is a covenant between us and Allah, an agreement?
This Ayah(آية‎) is talking about that agreement.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has made a covenant with us and that is we worship no one but Him,
and we witnessed upon ourselves that we shall not worship anyone but Allah.
And then Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
Lest you should say on the Day of Judgment that “we are unaware of this.”
Don't say, in other words, don’t say on the Day of Judgement that “I didn't know about that.”
We have given this covenant.
Two explanations have been given to this Ayah(آية).
One explanation says that this covenant is a covenant of Fitrah(فطرة‎).
Fitrah(فطرة‎) is the original state;
everyone of us has an original state, and that original state is Islam, Al-Fitrah(الفطرة‎).
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has created us on fitrah(فطرة‎).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says everyone is born on the fitrah(فطرة‎) of Islam, on the original creation of Islam,
and then their parents make them a Christian or a Jew or a Zoroastrian.
But in the beginning, we are Muslim.
Every one of us is Muslim and that’s why many who embrace Islam - they don’t like to be called “converts”;
they say: “We never converted to Islam, we reverted.
We reverted to Islam
because we were Muslim in the beginning and then we lost it and then we came back to it again.
So we are reverts because everyone of us started out as a Muslim submitting to Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
The next explanation is that
Allah سبحانه وتعالى took out the seed of Adam(آدم‎), every one of us, from Adam(آدم‎) until the Day of Judgment,
every one of us,
and we were placed in the Hand of Allah سبحانه وتعالى
and then Allah سبحانه وتعالى asked us;
Am I your Lord?
And we said: “Yes.”
And that is mentioned in a hadith(حديث‎).
Now the only reason why we have another opinion is that
is because some of the Ulema(علماء‎) critiqued this hadith(حديث‎).
Some of them accept it as strong and some don't.
But the hadith(حديث‎) is;
إن الله أخذ الميثاق من ظهر آدم  بنعمان - يوم عرفة - وأخرج من صلبه
كل ذرية ذرأها، فنثرهم بين يديه كالذر،
ثم كلمهم قبله، قال: أَلَسْتُ بِرَبِّكُمْ ۖ قَالُوا۟ بَلَىٰ
Allah has taken the covenant in Nuʿman(نعمان) - the Day of ʿArafah(عرفة).
Allah has taken out of Adam(آدَم) all of his seed and scattered them in His Hand like pearls,
then Allah asked them;
Isn’t it that I am your Lord?
They said: Yes.
According to this hadith(حديث‎), every one of us has spoken to Allah سبحانه وتعالى and said;
Yes, You are our Lord and we will worship nobody but You.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَعَلَّمَ ءَادَمَ ٱلْأَسْمَاءَ كُلَّهَا ثُمَّ عَرَضَهُمْ عَلَى ٱلْمَلَـٰئِكَةِ
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says: And He taught Adam(آدَم) all of the names.
In tafsir(تفسير‎), it mentions, this is the opinion of Sayyiduna Ibn Abbas رضي الله عنه,
that Allah سبحانه وتعالى taught him the names of everything
the nouns and the verbs and the adjectives, all the names.
And if we take this literally, it would mean that he knew the names of everything.
But then there is another meaning that is mentioned also,
and that is that Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given him the ability to identify objects
and to designate names for these objects,
and that is the ability of speaking a language.
Again, it’s the ability to identify objects and to designate names for these objects,
and we find that that is a human ability.
We have different languages in the world,
and all of these languages were founded by human beings by giving names to objects
and then finding verbs and adjectives to tie these things together.
Now imagine that we did not have this ability;
so you want to tell your friend about a tree,
you cannot name and identify that object
so what you have to do is take him to the tree,
or you want to tell him about an apple
you cannot describe the apple, you have to bring an apple to him and start pointing at it.
So Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given the son of Adam(آدم‎) this ability, and Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
خَلَقَ ٱلْإِنسَـٰنَ ۝ عَلَّمَهُ ٱلْبَيَانَ۝
Allah سبحانه وتعالى created the human and He taught him bayan(بيان), the ability of speaking, speech.
This is an ability that Allah سبحانه وتعالى did not give the angels.
The angels only know specific knowledge which Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given them
because they do not need this knowledge.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى taught them what they need.
They get orders, they receive orders from Allah سبحانه وتعالى and they do what they’re commanded.
يفعلون ما يؤمرون
But because the human being - Allah سبحانه وتعالى created him for the Khilafah(خلافة‎) on Earth.
عن عمارة الأرض
“To the establishment of the Khilafah(خِلَافَه) on Earth,” and to establish this earth and live in it.
That ability is necessary for us.
Imagine how our life would be;
actually, we wouldn't be living if we didn't have the ability to identify objects and name them.
This is a necessity for us to communicate,
and Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given the son of Adam(آدم‎) that ability.
So we’re able to name things,
and you find out that we’re producing every now and then thousands and thousands of objects
and we’re designating names to these objects,
microphone, speakers - all of these are new names,
but the son of Adam(آدم‎) is able and throw a thousand things in the market, we have the ability to find names for them.
وَعَلَّمَ ءَادَمَ ٱلْأَسْمَاءَ كُلَّهَا
Allah سبحانه وتعالى taught Adam (آدم‎) all of the names.
ثُمَّ عَرَضَهُمْ عَلَى ٱلْمَلَـٰئِكَةِ
And then Allah made a test and presented some objects on the angels.
فَقَالَ أَنبِـُٔونِى بِأَسْمَاءِ هَـٰؤُلَاءِ إِن كُنتُمْ صَـٰدِقِينَ۝
Tell Me the names of these if you are true. “if you are truthful, if you are right,”
because the angels, they said at the beginning;
“Why are You going to create a human being who will cause bloodshed and corruption?”
Allah سبحانه وتعالى made this test and told the angels to identify these objects.
What did the angels say?
قَالُوا سُبْحَـٰنَكَ لَا عِلْمَ لَنَا إِلَّا مَا عَلَّمْتَنَا ۖ إِنَّكَ أَنتَ ٱلْعَلِيمُ ٱلْحَكِيمُ۝
They said;
“Glory be to You, we have no knowledge but the knowledge that You have given us.”
إِنَّكَ أَنتَ ٱلْعَلِيمُ ٱلْحَكِيمُ۝
You are the Most Knowledgeable and the All-Wise.
And now it’s Adam(آدم‎)’s turn to go through the test.
قَالَ يَـٰـَٔادَمُ أَنبِئْهُم بِأَسْمَائِهِمْ
O Adam(آدَم), tell them these names.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
فَلَمَّا أَنبَأَهُم بِأَسْمَائِهِمْ قَالَ أَلَمْ أَقُل لَّكُمْ
أَلَمْ أَقُل لَّكُمْ إِنِّى أَعْلَمُ غَيْبَ ٱلسَّمَـٰوَٰتِ وَٱلْأَرْضِ
وَأَعْلَمُ مَا تُبْدُونَ وَمَا كُنتُمْ تَكْتُمُونَ۝
And when he told them the names, Allah سبحانه وتعالى told the angels;
Didn’t I tell you that I know the knowledge of the Unseen in the heavens and the earth
and I know what you reveal and what you conceal.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى knows all knowledge.
So Allah is telling the angels there is a hikmah(حكمة‎) for the creation of Adam(آدم‎) you don't know.
There is a hikmah(حكمة‎)‎ that you don't know,
and that is a lesson for us whenever we see something that we’re not able to understand or comprehend.
We need to understand that Allah has a wisdom behind it.
There is a hikmah(حكمة‎), there is a wisdom behind every action.
There is a hikmah(حكمة‎) behind everything
because many times human beings fall into that trap of questioning why some events are happening.
I mean, “Why is this happening?” And we question Qadr(قدر)
and we question misery and we question disease and we question disasters and we question wars.
“Why are these things happening?”
We need to realize Allah has a wisdom in everything that is happening around us, there is a reason.
We don't know it, Allah سبحانه وتعالى knows it.
So that's the story of the names.
Adam(آدم‎) was alone.
هُوَ ٱلَّذِى خَلَقَكُم مِّن نَّفْسٍ وَٰحِدَةٍ
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says you were created from one self, one nafs(نفس), one soul
and that is Adam(آدم‎).
And then Allah سبحانه وتعالى created out of Adam(آدم‎) his mate, Hawa(هوى‎).
And then the hadith(حديث‎) tells us that Hawa(هوى‎) was created from the rib of Sayyiduna Adam(سيدنا آدم‎).
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
يَـٰٓأَيُّهَا ٱلنَّاسُ ٱتَّقُوا۟ رَبَّكُمُ ٱلَّذِى خَلَقَكُم مِّن نَّفْسٍ وَٰحِدَةٍ
وَخَلَقَ مِنْهَا زَوْجَهَا
وَبَثَّ مِنْهُمَا رِجَالًا كَثِيرًا وَنِسَآءً ۚ
وَٱتَّقُوا۟ ٱللَّهَ ٱلَّذِى تَسَآءَلُونَ بِهِۦ وَٱلْأَرْحَامَ ۚ
إِنَّ ٱللَّهَ كَانَ عَلَيْكُمْ رَقِيبًا۝
O mankind, be dutiful to your Lord who created you from a single person,
and from him He created his wife, and from them both He created many men and women.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ says in the Hadith(حديث);
استوصوا بالنساء خيرا
فإن المرأة خلقت من ضلع
وإن أعوج شيء في الضلع أعلاه
فإن ذهبت تقيمه كسرته وإن تركته لم يزل أعوج فاستوصوا بالنساء خيرا
متفق عليه
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: “Take good care of women.
Women were created from a rib,
and the most bent part of the rib is the top of it.
If you try to make it straight, you'll break it,
and if you leave it, it’ll remain bent, so take good care of women.
If we understand this hadith(حديث‎), the communication between men and women would be much better and easier.
Adam(آدم‎) and Hawa(هوى‎) were living in Jannah(جنة).
They had all of Jannah(جنة‎), but there was an exception and that is the tree.
One tree, now what type of tree is this?
Apple tree? Banana tree? Asking this question, to start with, is part of
علم لا ينفع
knowledge that does not benefit.
Going into this is part of the knowledge that does not benefit and that's why Allah سبحانه وتعالى did not mention it in Qur’an.
The details of these stories are not mentioned in Qur’an - what type of tree was it, what’s the name of it, how long it was.
I mean, just like for example, in the story of the people of the cave,
to show you that Allah سبحانه وتعالى is telling us about knowledge that would benefit us
but sometimes we try to go into areas that would not benefit us.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى left it
and we try to go and investigate(wrong practice).
In the story of the young men, when they went in the cave,
وَكَلْبُهُم بَـٰسِطٌ ذِرَاعَيْهِ بِٱلْوَصِيدِ
It says that their dog was spreading its arms on the entrance of the cave.
Some started questioning: “what type of dog was it”?
and “what’s the color of the dog”?
Some of them said: “It's white” and some of them said: “It’s black” and some of them said: “No, it’s a mixture of black and white.”
I mean, what kind of benefit can we learn from this knowledge? Nothing.
The reason why these stories are mentioned in Qur’an are not as a historical account,
but they are mentioned for their Ibrah(عبرة).
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
لَعَلَّهُمْ يَتَفَكَّرُونَ
So that they may contemplate.
And Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
عِبْرَةٌ لِّأُولِى ٱلْأَلْبَـٰابِ
These are lessons for the ones of understanding.
So the tree was mentioned in Qur’an;
شَجَرَةِ ٱلْخُلْدِ
It’s just a tree,
but we do not know what kind of tree was it and where it was and how tall it was…
we don’t know those details.
It was a tree
that is the only part of Jannah(جنة‎) Adam(آدم‎) and Hawa(هوى‎) were not supposed to touch.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَقُلْنَا يَـٰـَٔادَمُ ٱسْكُنْ أَنتَ وَزَوْجُكَ ٱلْجَنَّةَ
وَكُلَا مِنْهَا رَغَدًا حَيْثُ شِئْتُمَا
وَلَا تَقْرَبَا هَـٰذِهِ ٱلشَّجَرَةَ فَتَكُونَا مِنَ ٱلظَّـٰلِمِينَ۝
And We said: O Adam(آدَم), live, and your mate, in Jannah(جنة) and eat from it wherever you want,
but do not touch this tree.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
فَوَسْوَسَ إِلَيْهِ ٱلشَّيْطَـٰنُ
Shaitan(شيطان) gave Adam(آدم‎) waswasah(وسوسة).
Waswasah(وسوسة) is some hidden speech that he’s delivering in one's mind, evil inspiration.
What did Iblis(إبليس), Shaytan(شيطان) tell Adam (آدم‎)?
Did he tell Adam(آدم‎): “Go and eat from the tree Allah told you: ‘Don't touch’”?
Did he tell Adam(آدم‎): “Go and disobey Allah سبحانه وتعالى”?
Did he tell him: “Go and commit Haram(حرام)”?
He knew how to deal with the human being.
فَوَسْوَسَ إِلَيْهِ ٱلشَّيْطَـٰنُ
قَالَ يَـٰـَٔادَمُ هَلْ أَدُلُّكَ عَلَىٰ شَجَرَةِ ٱلْخُلْدِ وَمُلْكٍ لَّا يَبْلَىٰ
He said: Shall I tell you about the tree that will give you infinite life, eternity,
and will give you the greatest kingdom that will not end?
Shaytan(شيطان) knows our points of weakness and that's where he attacks from.
He didn't go to Adam(آدم‎) bluntly and tell him;
“Go and disobey Allah سبحانه وتعالى.” Otherwise, Adam(آدم‎) wouldn't have done it.
He told him: This tree would give you continuous life, eternal life,
and it would give you kingdom.
Adam(آدم‎) and Hawa(هوى‎) - they ate from that tree, and because of that, Allah سبحانه وتعالى sent them down to Earth.
Whenever you read this Ayah(آية) or hear about this story,
do you ever wonder how could such a great Nabi(نبي) commit such a mistake?
Do you ever wonder how come Allah سبحانه وتعالى told him: “Don't touch from that tree”
and then he went and ate from it?
Do you ever wonder how could that happen?
I think some of you may had that idea.
How come, this is a Nabi(نبي) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى, how could he do that?
By the way, at that time, he was not a Nabi(نبي) yet,
but later in Earth, he became of the Ambiya(أنبياء‎).
Instead of thinking about why Adam(آدم‎) did so,
why not think about yourself that you are committing sins and mistakes.
It is much more difficult to understand how we can commit sins
because, with Adam(آدم‎), he did not have any experience whatsoever;
he did not know about Shaytan(شيطان), he had only knowledge about Shaytan(شيطان), but he had no experience with him.
An experience is different than knowledge.
With Adam(آدم‎), he knew that Shaytan(شيطان) is his enemy, but he never experienced it.
And even Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
ليس الخبر كالمعاينة
“Knowing the news is not like seeing it.”
Adam(آدم‎) had the knowledge, but he didn't have any experience with Shaytan(شيطان) yet.
We know what happened to Adam(آدم‎) and we know it was caused by Shaytan(شيطان)
and we have seen a long history, of mankind and we’re still committing the same mistake again and again.
We should question that, we should not question the fact that Adam(آدم‎) committed this mistake
because for Adam(آدم‎), it was a very innocent mistake,
and Allah سبحانه وتعالى forgave him
because Adam(آدم‎) did not have any experience yet and Allah سبحانه وتعالى wanted this to be a test for Adam(آدم‎)
so that he could learn from it and this could be experience for Adam(آدم‎) to prepare him
because he will be a Nabi(نبي) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
It's a preparation for Adam(آدم‎); Allah’s preparing him
just like Allah سبحانه وتعالى was preparing Dawud(داود) through the mistake that he committed and we’re gonna talk about that.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى was preparing Dawud(داود) for the position of Khilafah(خلافة‎)
so Allah سبحانه وتعالى made him go through that judgment and he made a mistake in it
and then Allah سبحانه وتعالى corrected that mistake for him.
They say that Dawud(داود), after the mistake, was better than he was before.
So Allah سبحانه وتعالى was preparing Adam(آدم‎) so that he would go through this experience and learn from it
and it would prepare him for living on this earth to realize that Shaytan(شيطان), Iblis(إبليس), is your enemy.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَقُلْنَا ٱهْبِطُوا بَعْضُكُمْ لِبَعْضٍ عَدُوٌّ
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says: Get you down, all.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى told Adam(آدم‎) and Hawa(هوى‎) to get out of Jannah(جنة‎).
In Arabic, there is singular, which is for one, and then there is another form for two and then there is plural for three and more.
In English, we have only singular and plural;
singular is for one, plural is for how many?
Two or more.
In English, if you are talking about two people, you say “they”. You don’t say “he”.
“They”
it’s two of them.
But in Arabic, plural is not 2, plural is three or more.
There is another form that is used for the two.
Adam(آدم‎) and Hawa(هوى‎) are two.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى referred to them in the plural form.
ٱهْبِطُوا۟
All of you…
All of you descend down from Jannah(جنة) in a plural form…
but they were only two.
Al-Farah(الفرح) says, one of the Mufassireen(مفسرين‎), he says;
Because this command is to Adam(آدم‎) and his wife and all of us with them.
All of us were in Jannah(جنة‎), that's where we were.
But because of Iblis(إبليس) and Shaytan(شيطان) and that mistake, we all came down to Duniya(دنيا‎).
So we do not really belong to Duniya(دنيا‎)
this is not where we belong to.
We are here for a temporary time, we belong to Al-Akhirah(الآخرة‎).
وَلَكُمْ فِى ٱلْأَرْضِ مُسْتَقَرٌّ وَمَتَـٰعٌ إِلَىٰ حِينٍ۝
On Earth will be a dwelling place for you and an enjoyment for a time.
You’re gonna stay there for a while.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى taught Adam(آدم‎) some words to learn.
فَتَلَقَّىٰ ءَادَمُ مِن رَّبِّهِۦ كَلِمَـٰتٍ فَتَابَ عَلَيْهِ ۚ
إِنَّهُۥ هُوَ ٱلتَّوَّابُ ٱلرَّحِيمُ۝
Then Adam(آدَم) received from his Lord words, and His Lord pardoned him and accepted his repentance.
Verily, He is the One who forgives.
So Allah taught Adam(آدم‎) words to say, Allah taught Adam(آدم‎) a Dua(دُعَا) to say, and then Allah سبحانه وتعالى forgave him.
What was this Dua(دُعَا)?
قَالَا رَبَّنَا ظَلَمْنَا أَنفُسَنَا
وَإِن لَّمْ تَغْفِرْ لَنَا وَتَرْحَمْنَا لَنَكُونَنَّ مِنَ ٱلْخَـٰسِرِينَ۝
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
They said: Our Lord, we have wronged ourselves.
If You forgive us not and bestow not upon us Your mercy, we shall certainly be of the losers.
We have wronged ourselves. Look at this Dua(دُعَا),
very important Dua(دُعَا), and please memorize it and use it because it is the Duʿa(دعاء) of the sinners.
رَبَّنَا ظَلَمْنَا أَنفُسَنَا
O Allah, we have wronged ourselves, we have committed wrong
and we have harmed ourselves by this wrong, we’re not harming Allah, we’re harming our own selves.
وَإِن لَّمْ تَغْفِرْ لَنَا وَتَرْحَمْنَا
If You do not have forgiveness on us and mercy, we would be of the losers.
If you do not forgive us and have mercy on us, we would be losers.
We need You, O Allah, so please, O Allah, we beg You to forgive us and have mercy on us.
This is the Duʿa(دعاء) that Allah سبحانه وتعالى taught Adam(آدم‎) and Hawa(هوى‎).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ